<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming | Hello, World</title>
    <link>https://nixramirez.github.io/tags/programming/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nixramirez.github.io/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Programming</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Programming</title>
      <link>https://nixramirez.github.io/tags/programming/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Seasons in React.js</title>
      <link>https://nixramirez.github.io/project/reactfirstproj/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nixramirez.github.io/project/reactfirstproj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a proud moment - the first front-end I&amp;rsquo;ve built with React.js and JSX! It&amp;rsquo;s very simple, but it taught me a lot on how React worked internally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This app displays either two screens dependent on whether it’s summer or winter wherever the user is currently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user in New Zealand (i.e. me) is in the southern hemisphere where it’s currenty winter (May 2nd, when this blogpost was written). The app displays the winter screen in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;winterscreen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Winter Screen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user in San Francisco, on the other hand, is in the northern hemisphere where it’s currently summer. The app displays the summer screen for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;summerscreen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Summer Screen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we know where the user is? Well, we can detect user location with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Geolocation_API&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mozilla Geolocation API&lt;/a&gt;
. We can grab latitude and longitude information about the user from this service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also force the Google Chrome browser to consider a location like San Francisco away from us by changing its geolocation in its ‘Sensors’ tab like so (mostly for testing the different views):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;forcelocationchange.png&#34; alt=&#34;Force location change&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the user has disabled location-sharing in any-way, the screen below encourages them to enable it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;acceptlocationscreen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Accept location screen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semantic UI and some CSS was used to style the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project taught me React&amp;rsquo;s fundamentals - class based and functional components, the component life cycle methods, how to update component state, and how to pass information down from parent to children components using the props system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently building and deploying a more complex full-stack web app, integrating node.js/express.js for the back-end and a mongodb database. I might write a tutorial on that when it&amp;rsquo;s done, so if you&amp;rsquo;re interested, please stay tuned for that post! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro To Python Workshop</title>
      <link>https://nixramirez.github.io/project/pythonworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nixramirez.github.io/project/pythonworkshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project, I taught an introductory workshop on Python&amp;rsquo;s base syntax, plus some basic libraries for working with data (i.e. pandas, numpy, matplotlib).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was done for the University of Auckland Data Science Club, which I help run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was one workshop in a series teaching essential end-to-end data science skills. Workshops on Data Cleaning, Data Visualisation and Data modelling were planned for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work as a programming tutor, so I thought teaching such a workshop would be easy. &lt;strong&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I had to come up with &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; of the material on my own &amp;ndash; the recordings, the jupyter notebooks, the coding challenges, and sourcing the data-set. The recorded format also made it all the more daunting, as any mistakes I made would go on record officially! I also worried about delivering an engaging workshop. After all, the online nature of the workshop meant people could drop out anytime they wished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were surprised to see good engagement with this workshop, though, with people attending our Live Q&amp;amp;A sessions after the workshop to ask for help regarding our coding challenges. This suggested people were watching our videos &amp;lsquo;til the end. I&amp;rsquo;ve also received positive verbal feedback about the workshop from members, and the youtube view count for both videos suggested pretty good engagement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was such a rewarding experience, which highlighted a few things: 1.) Teaching isn&amp;rsquo;t easy 2.) Teaching is &lt;strong&gt;very hard&lt;/strong&gt; to get right 3.) I love teaching and sharing the beauty of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I present, the University of Auckland Data Science Club&amp;rsquo;s Intro to Python workshop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-one-python-base-snytax&#34;&gt;Part One: Python Base Snytax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/S6hwKDvI24c&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-two-python-for-data-science&#34;&gt;Part Two: Python for Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/n9X6ObJ9kos&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materials accompanying the workshop are 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1o3mH_-6ANT7EfiFWV31IXbhkc9P8VsAn?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;
. These include the Jupyter notebooks used in both parts, a set of coding challenges to try after going through the workshop (and their associated answers), and the data-set used in part two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please reach out if you have any feedback or queries! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
